so let's talk about
this particular suta today
particular suta today
it's from the angutsu nikaya
and it's called assemblies and it's
about community
community
community harmony monks
these are the three communities or
assemblies what three
a community of the best a divided
community and
a harmonious community
and what is a community of the best
a community where the senior monks the
elders of the community
are not indulgent or slack
nor are they backslided
instead they take the lead in seclusion
rousing energy for the or the attaining
the unattained
achieving the energy
and realizing the unrealized
and those who come afterwards follow
their example
they too are not indulgent or slack nor
are they backsliders instead they take
the lead in seclusion
browsing energy for the attaining of the
unattained this is called the assembly of the best
this is called the assembly of the best
the community of the best and the
and the
what is the divided community a
community where the monks argue quarrel
fight continually wounding each other
with barbed words or
barbed words or
uh what they call it a verbal stabbing
each other verbal daggers this is called
the divided
community and what is the harmonious community
and what is the harmonious community
a community where the monks live in
harmony they are peaceable uncontentious
they are peaceable uncontentious
or mudita with each other
without quarreling blending like milk
and water and regarding each other with
kindly eyes
this is the harmonious assembly
and just just the last bit when the
monks live in harmony like this they
make much merit at that time the monks
live in a
heavenly situation that's my translation
for the brahmavihara they live in a
heavenly situation
that is
the liberated mind of non-contention or
the unconstricted mind of non-contention
the mind of medita
when they are pleased happiness brings
up springs up when the mind is happy
the body becomes calm when the body is
calm they feel at ease and when they are
at ease the mind becomes composed
so there's a there's a simile at the end
but i i won't go into that
there you go
[Music]
how to bring
you know how to have a harmonious
community whether it's you know
whether it's you know
monastic or
or just a householder you know your
family any community how to have
any community how to have
harmony
i don't go about that
and for me it seems to suggest there
that
when i think about harmony
you know
you yourself have to be
practicing harmonious qualities
you can't be you can't be doing things
which give rise to
give rise to
trouble for yourself or others
unharmonious qualities and wholesome
qualities you can't be doing that
and expecting some
uh
basic unity
within yourself or outside of yourself
yeah impossible yeah
well so first things like um
people people often confuse um
obedience for harmony
that's not necessarily harmonious you
know people might not voice
their disagreement due to one reason or
the other you know the authoritative set
up or something but that doesn't mean
they regard each other with friendly
eyes um um
yeah
so so then
you ask yourself or anybody can ask
himself what is the what is the true
cause of this harmony
is it behavior of others
or is it ill will in my mind
is it uh
the the mental pressure
of uh annoyance and aversion that i
cannot live with thus i am addressing
the circumstances
and trying to change the world or people
around me so i don't have to go through
these mental states
is that the reason for this harmony or
is it the genuine
things that other people do and then we
just need to fix their behavior and
we'll live in perfect harmony
so obviously the answer is quite evident
but that's that's the reason really
so
[Music] the reason for this harmony in any
the reason for this harmony in any
community including the world itself
it's the minds of individuals
but that's
that's hard to
it's not that hard to see but it's kind
of hard to admit
because well first of all
it's painful
mind of aversion is painful so you want
to get rid of it
second of all
you do also want to see an immediate
result of your effort towards harmony or
of your effort towards harmony or
whatever else
and you're not going to see an immediate
result if you are the only one
just basically addressing your mind
while everybody else seems to not care
about it but then you realize oh but
that's something you are also getting
annoyed over
so one way or the other
you end up acting out of annoyance
and that's exactly what other people do
they act out of their annoyances and
that's why there is no harmony
so it's not about
fabricating you know using
psychotherapeutical methods and stuff
to regard each other with friendly eyes
and just visualize the friendship no
it's removing your own resistance to
your own mind of ill will
overcoming your own ill will
means you will see everybody as a friend
basically in that sense you will not be
able to hate them
um
and now if every individual in that that
assembly does that that is a perfect
that is a divine community because every
individual addressed the root of the
problem as opposed to ignored the root of the
as opposed to ignored the root of the
problem acted out of the root of the
problem and changed the world the way he
thinks it should be
so whether it's assembly of three people
or five people or the entire world
the root of the issue is always agreed
aversion delusion
but you know like oh well it's not gonna
happen that everybody will address that
so i better then
kind of attack others or try to change
others and get a shortcut to the
solution of the problem but failing to
understand that
problem is still there
the framework of the problem
the framework of the problem greed
diversion delusion has remained
unchanged because you just fed it and
acted out of it
and that's that's pretty much just like
a symptom of when people
want to change the world
knowing themselves they carry those
issues they're complaining against and
trying to change in others they're
carrying themselves but they kind of act
out a convention
conviction that as long as they change
the world first then they'll be all
right as well but it's not it's putting
the cart in front of the horse
first things first and that's your own
great diversion delusion that's what
buddha said in arahant a person who has
completely approved the greater vision
derivation has practiced for the benefit
of the world as well
even if he doesn't care about the world
the fact is
there is one individual
that has uprooted the source of all
problems of the entire samsara of
everything and that's the greatest contribution to
and that's the greatest contribution to
the world you can make
you know you can legislate you can agree
you can learn the modes of
behavior and etiquette how relate to
each other so you know so we don't argue
and so on but fundamentally
the community
the wellness or the community
is measured by you know it's
the wellness the healthiness of
individuals the mental health of
individuals are they free from greed aversion
are they free from greed aversion
delusion
or are they not are they acting on a
kind of a social agreement or on account
of simply not being able to have ill
will towards each other
and hence that's a divine community
you know you're not gonna reach
you're not sorry you're not gonna reach
a divine community by by uh you know
creating a perfect social agreement that
we all share the same values and ethical
convictions and so on yeah but mentally
still greater version delusions sooner
or later agree the word delusion will
have to
find its way in a negative in a negative
manner because it's still there because
our social agreement is rooted in
greater virgin delusion because we
didn't want to deal with the mind we
wanted to address the society and then
have things in order that way which is
kind of
immediately satisfying and more very
quick uh quicker to verify and more
pleasing in other words we were acting
out of our desires and wanted to satisfy
our desire for a perfect order for what
we think the perfect order is
but the root of the problem is the
desire so
so
unless that changes
exactly exactly individual desires so
unless that changes framework remains
the same so the problem has not been
resolved just permutated just permutated
yes
if you do
if you claim to
care for others
then you know you you really should see
you know you you really should see
that it is you have to now remove those
unwholesome things within yourself well
yeah you can you can care for others
you can care for others but then you ask
yourself yes but am i caring out of
yes but am i caring out of
desire towards others towards order of
the world that requires others
or do i care because i am desireless
because i have no uh capacity for your
will lust or distraction so i just
simply wish people well on paper both
people care but one is simply rooted in
i care because i want to satisfy my
desire of a perfect world that i like to
think i'm living in and so on and that's
not that's not i mean it's not as
that's not i mean it's not as
unwholesome as not caring at all
but it's certainly not
wholesome on the level of uprooting your
desire and really fixing the problem
kind of feel that
like oh well if i just start uploading
my desires there is nothing immediately
verifying it the world seems to ignore
my contribution there is no feedback
there is nothing there is no reward
there is no satisfaction
so then it's just easier to just yeah
but let's just go and change the world
let's let's unite us all of us and
change the world for the better
while individually we act out of the
same desires that those people who
change the world for the world had
so the desire that's what i said the
desire is the most blame word
you can have all sorts of you know lofty
ethical standards moral standards that's
nice but it's all well within samsara
makes no difference to samsara
so are you talking from the point of
view of
simply having kind of you know an
agreeable pleasant life in the current society for
pleasant life in the current society for
which you know you don't need buddha's
instruction just from common sense or
are you talking for like a genuine you
know uprooting of the problem
fixing the individuals towards
liberation and that's why the buddha
compared that type of community to like
community of brahmas because it's
nothing short of that
yeah but even even even in the worldly sense
but even even even in the worldly sense
you know if a
individual is uh practicing wholesome things you
is uh practicing wholesome things you
know restraining themselves having some
values in immorality
and restraining themselves
that's already the community that will
um grow around that person it is it will
be you know a heavenly type of situation
eventually yeah yeah but that's where
the patience has to come in
people basically people people like even
if they know that the root of the
problem is a desire
they feel justified in aiming at the
other people at the society at the
arrangements aiming at the you know that
level of change
because they feel like well there is not
enough time
it takes too much time for me to be
addressing my own you know
um desires and cravings you know tidy up
my own room it just takes too much time
for that let's just go and tidy up a
mess around us and then we'll tidy up
the rooms but the mess around us is the
mess of individual untidy rooms
that's it
but they feel like there is not enough
time so they feel justified in in sort
of addressing it on that projected level
but the problem is you're not
you're not addressing anything because
again the the problem of the mess is the
the the problem of the mess is the
problem that every individual brings to
its own desires
and if that's
if that has not been addressed means the
framework for the mass remains you have
just reordered it in a pleasing manner
it's still the same mess
and but yes even in in like a
but yes even in in like a
completely worldly terms
it would still actually matter if you if
you not just address your own desires tidy
not just address your own desires tidy
up your own room but actually if that's
the example you set
that's when you have like a you know
back in the day they would have talked
about it when you have wholesome
societies when these values were shared
among people
so they were not confused they were not
impatient they were not lying to
themselves or convincing themselves that
they should be you know addressing
things on the level of the world but
they knew to take responsibility for
their own desires for their own
behaviors for their own virtue and
morality and then the community was fine
and then the community was fine
because if every individual addresses
its own domain
the collection of those individuals i
the society will have no issues
but somebody has to start it especially
once the society has lost its ways
in terms of you know ethical standard
and virtue and so on yes somebody has to
start re-educating in that sense through
its own example
not through force or like brainwashing
basically because that that's again
rooted in your own desires you're not
changing anything
so yeah you want a a a united community
a harmonious you must
harmonize yourself exactly and that
means you must remain within or you must
remain in internal harmony
even if others are not doing what you're
doing yeah now as you say such there needs to
yeah now as you say such there needs to
be
someone needs to start that
and such a person
you know being amongst you know who has
elders who are unwholesome the whole
society is unwholesome the community the
mother father brothers and sisters
everyone's unwholesome
and then that one person besides
understands wholesome and sticks to that
that is amazing and then for a community to
is amazing and then for a community to
grow around that person amazing yeah and
then there is
it's incredible
uh the buddha for example you know
the great a great example
but there are other communities out
there in the world has happened uh
presently in the past that there's
always had to be some person who had to
do that yeah and then there were always
elders there were always elders in the
community who had to keep on doing that
yeah yeah you know
and those elders have to
in a way
you have to realize the responsibility
that you have you know as a parent
as an elder a leader in the community
that yeah people are looking up to you there
yeah people are looking up to you there
are there's newcomers
so
you know for for for
[Music] the welfare of future generations you
the welfare of future generations you
need to keep up this harmony
you need to keep the standard of
business yeah yeah i mean you're doing it for
yeah yeah i mean you're doing it for
yourself basically you just incidentally
is contributing for the welfare of the
future generations
but you are doing it because you prefer
to do it because exactly through the
practice of doing it
you have uprooted the desire the
aversion and and the unwholesome
qualities so now you actually prefer to
stay in that mode you have no desire to
return back to you know chasing desires
and and and being
um
projected out there onto the world and
trying to change the circumstances and
so on which all kind of pla implies
your desire one way or the other yes yes
like
just that responsibility in a way from
the disciples of that teacher
or the one that learned from that elder
you know if you want your community to
be harmonious for generations to come
then you need to do that work internally
yeah but again again like like whether
you want the community or not you
realize it doesn't matter
you don't have even if you have no
desire towards any community
if you have grouped a desire put a
desire in yourself that is setting the
example whether you want it or not
whether you intend to do that or not
if you're practicing a wholesome things
developing wholesome qualities uh
whether you want to or not
harmony is the result yeah yeah one way
or the other that is being
perceived by others even if you don't
necessarily make a mission out of you
know showing the world and changing
everybody through your own you know inner harmony
through your own you know inner harmony
and practicing virtue and so on it will
stand out it will be for the benefit it
will be for the benefit of the world
and the opposite you know even if you
are wishing harmony yeah
exactly but you are acting on wholesome you're
but you are acting on wholesome you're
doing awesome things well no matter how
much you wish is not going to work out
yeah yeah
and that's that's pretty much that's the
problem always you know like
people generally today operate on the on
that projected level of the world the
views are on the level of the world
responsibilities on the level of the
world blame the world you know blame the
blame the world you know blame the
governments blame the this kind of
you know
more distant sense of others all right
other people but again it's all rooted
in the individuals
so unless you yourself
are free from desire you are equally
blameword and that's exactly what the
buddha said the only blameless one is
the one that has a proto-degree
diversion delusion
he cannot be he can be blamed but he's
blameless none of that blame sticks to
him because he's not partaking in the
because he's not partaking in the
framework of the problem which is desire
one thing you said a little while ago uh
i think within the one of the youtube
videos that
when someone was asking about uh war
going to war and that you were saying
that you know somebody
to end
hate to end the war somebody has to take
the punch
and not retaliate not retaliate that's
that's kind of what you were saying
someone has to take it
yeah there is going to be a fight
somewhere along the line someone's going
to come and punch you but if you want to
fight to stop then you gotta you can't
retaliate yeah you're going to have to
take that
and just let it cool down
yeah someone could do yeah exactly and
that's that's you know so what do you
value do you do you truly value
do you do you truly value
peace non-violence
non-violence
are those your standards
or if pushed your standards are to well
i'm gonna have a last say or a last
punch in which case well see you don't
truly value those things that you say
you value so injustice
so injustice
injustice violence that is what the
world is because world is rooted in
desire because world is made out of
individuals whereby every single living
being acts out of the desire
acts out of the desire
and that's that's why there are problems
i mean they would have said that himself
sons fight with fathers fathers with
mothers with daughters kings with kings
countries with the countries why because
of the central desire that's it that's
the sole reason
for all the conflict within one family
or multiple families or the entire
kingdoms essential these desires that's
it people's desires
they will have to reach a conflict
because not all desires can be the same
so
if you truly value the end of conflict
means you must truly value ending of
your own desire not act out of desire
for the ending of the conflict becomes a
contradiction in terms
you know uh people can
be unified
with hate you know we are friends
because we hate we hate this we hate the
same thing yeah common enemy yeah
common enemy and then when we knew
now who are friends because we hate the
commentary we go and we destroy that
enemy and everything's fine life goes back to
and everything's fine life goes back to
normal
we come back into our homes
and what do we still have we still have
that value of hatred or fighting of killing
value of hatred or fighting of killing
of
by fighting against
that which
is uncomfortable for us we don't want
that which is unacceptable to us yeah we
have that attitude yeah and so now
what's going on
now we were friends united in hate
now we're enemy we'll be
fighting you fighting with your father
you know friends
exactly and before long
and before long
and before long we might become someone
else's unifying enemy
and the world go here
and world goes back to normal for the
time being how is that measured that's
measured by ah
i go back to my desires that i can
fulfill
my safety my sensuality the access to
the senses that's how people measure
normality through to basically how much their
through to basically how much their
desires regain access
to things they want
and because of that then
you are
like at peril of uh of losing it because
the slightest change in circumstances
internally or externally
you will lose the access means you will
lose the safety means you're back to
where you were before so all your
victories meant nothing
yeah turmoil
basically and that that comes down to that other
and that that comes down to that other
thing the possessions we spoke about
before that that's what makes you liable
to suffer
and this um
when it says in the suture
when when the monks live in
harmony like this they make much men at
that time the monks live in a heavenly
situation this is the liberated mind of vegeta
this is the liberated mind of vegeta
yeah
but the mind
the mind
liberated as unconstricted you know
yeah yeah not bound not not basically
tethered to to the weight of desires and
to to the weight of desires and
possessions and and central
satisfactions and so
on so
so that mind
being liberated being unconstricted
being so large and expansive
you know
when something occurs
in the world uh
whatever happens a natural disaster or
an army comes and destroys you
that mind which has been liberated
through acts of wholesome acts through acts of
acts of wholesome acts through acts of
peace
values of peace and so on and wisdom
exactly and wisdom
doesn't get moved that mind is
harmonious it's a harmony that
a samadhi which is moved yeah it's
composed it's composed on the level that
cannot be perturbed
by changes in the world no matter of the
the that's of the the scale of the
changes
and that's pretty much why what
everybody wants
even people that go and
fight for desires and try to change
things and you know
modify the world
they do because for the same reason
they don't want their minds to be
perturbed by things that are disagreeable
by things that are disagreeable
so although it's a it's a it's a uh good
intention it's sort of um aimed at the
wrong things it's aimed at the wrong
it's aimed to basically where the
problem isn't
and that's that's why the harmony that
the buddha talks about
it's measured by the mind states of
those individuals
not by the as i said by the etiquette
and you know how often they bow to each
other and softness of the words that
they use no it's measured by the
inability to have thoughts of ill will
towards each other
like genuinely minds minds are so
developed expanded through correct endurance
expanded through correct endurance
proper understanding virtue and so on
that they cannot
they cannot
turn towards each other with their will
it's just impossible inconceivable
taking up ill will becomes inconceivable
and that's the perfect harmony that's
why the the the pure is the cleanest the
the best of the assemblies it's like the
assembly of arahants as we said you know
it's the highest merit you get by by
helping that type of assembly
it's basically assembly of individuals
it's not a group arahants are not a
group it's every individual fully
purified so imagine the purity of a group when
so imagine the purity of a group when
there is no group is just individuals
free from greed diversion delusion
that's the divine assembly
assembly that has not projected its
views on the level of others and they
and us
and the group that that group ownership
that dissolves your individual
responsibility that covers this up
covers it up the group identity none of
that exists in an assembly of our hands
they are unmoved by any of that
and that's why they are the purest and
the highest and
and
i was just thinking about the word you
know harmony harmony
wise
when two people are in harmony you could
also say that they are in in agreement
with each other
yeah there's no disagreement but but you can
there's no disagreement but but you can
as with anything else that can have two
meanings you can have a worldly meaning
or you can have a meaning that pertains
to the practice of dharma so
are in harmony because we do the same
things externally
or we are in harmony because both of our
minds have developed in the same
direction of uprooting ill will
lust delusion and everything else so
that is also a type of harmony
it's just not visible and measurable
harmony as as you know uniformity is
the the mind which is
in agreement
this might be the mind which is in
agreement with reality
there is a
concord with reality
it doesn't um
it's not in a different agreement with
reality it's it's not taking feelings as mine
it's it's not taking feelings as mine
right yeah well see no i mean reality is
not the best word there because
yeah for the mind not developed reality
is its desire
is its great diversion delusion that is
the reality
very real reality
well what is a better word than
well i don't why would you need a better
word just harmony
yeah the mind yeah
so the mind that it's basically in
agreement with the principle of
non-ill will or you can say
desirelessness and any of those terms yeah the
and any of those terms yeah the
agreement with any of that
means you will be developed in that
regard
in tune with you could say that yeah [Music]
[Music]
exactly with the principles of dharma
not in that some sort of esoterical
sense but simply with the principles of
but simply with the principles of
non-ill will
non-aversion non-lust non-distraction
non-desire so tune yourself to that or to any of
so tune yourself to that or to any of
that for that matter and you are heading
in the right direction
but when i say tune yourself to that
doesn't mean have wishful thinking that
tunes you to that but actually act
accordingly and put that as the criteria for your
and put that as the criteria for your
behavior by body speech and mind now
basically by being virtuous by seeing
the danger in the slightest fault
by being moderate in eating by guarding
of the sense those not giving in to
sensual desires
by not uh acting out a will will out of
things that annoy you by bearing it and
enduring it as would have said the way
you would endure the elements then you
will understand sure and then yes you
will be in tune
but it's not a question of figuring it
out so to be in tune the question is of
enduring it rightly
putting in the work of non-acting and so
on not acting out and so on and then you
will be in tune yes
yeah then you will align yourself with
those principles